good evening
i deeply appreciate the opportunity
to introduce
my dear friend
ander cook
it probably will not come as a surprise
to anybody in this room
when i tell you
that anda has been
a bright light
in many of our personal
and political darknesses
she knows
how to celebrate feasts
and how to console during famines
she's a great cook she's a wonderful
host house hostess
she stayed
faithful to latvia
despite of all her commitment to ohio
and the beautiful city
green city on the blue lake here on the
uec
she's always worked
for a better world
and
has been only
[Music]
committed more than
than to
her community
to her own family and especially her
devoted
spouse other is a born leader
any group she joined she sooner or later
became president
and
she's also
a creative artist
her writing her music
her photography have been a blessing to
us all
so
this great daughter of latvia
and wonderful citizens of the world
she was given the key of the city of
cleveland and she's always
that had the key to our hearts
[Applause]
thank you great daughter of austria
excuse my reading but i just had to say
something
good evening everybody
i'm truly um to receive this honor
when i came to cleveland i didn't know
so
and yet after these many years i have
been enriched with many friendships
and associate associations that have
created the person who is me
first of all my husband
bill
who continuously inspires and challenges
me
with his own many interests and
accomplishments
our children
grandchildren
and even great-grandchildren
have that nose created a different name
my dear friend dad marcellus
who for some 50 past years
has endured my stubbornness
in our discussions and deliberations
the latvian community
embracing me and allowing me to
participate in different capacities has
strengthened my latvian values and then
of course
the former colleagues
and members of organizations
that have enhanced my love for cleveland
and america
so who am i
when my family left latvia in september
of 1944
it was through the intention to return
after the war
the furniture and the piano were covered
and the king was left at the outside
door
but it was not to be
in 1973
almost 30 years after leaving
when the airplane
[Music]
wheels
touched the
latvian soul
i couldn't stop the tears
i was even more emotionally broad
seeing my father who
who had come to the airport to greet me
and we had not seen each other for since
i had left latvia he had been sent to
siberia
and i had not seen him suit leaving
latvia
on that trip our two daughters lisa inda
and my mother accompanied me
while bill stayed home with our son john
who was too young to travel
this trip
was during christmas holidays
the soviets regime was in full force we
were not to go outside to reveal
lightning's capital blessed with their
prescribed soviet travel groups
all the hotel rooms were involved
and the only place for decent shopping
was a foreign currency stores that were
off limits to their local people
christmas eve was spent with my father
but he had to cover windows for fear
someone might support the forbidden
celebration of christmas
new year's eve was a special celebration
at the rita hotel
i was with our daughters
and after so many years with both my
parents
how perfect could that be but then
some american students who were staying
at the hotel
started singing online sign
fierce dear skiers
missing bill and john and realizing the
love i hope for america
and thank all of you for an opportunity
to learn and to love thank you
[Applause]
thank
thank you